welcome back to 25-minute physiology I'm
dr. Andy Galpin today we're talking
carbs fat and protein now most people
unless they're on a specialized diet
most people are gonna have some sort of
a reasonable split between the amount of
protein fat and carbohydrate that they
ingest throughout the day now depending
on your situation you might change the
proportions of some of these and we'll
get to those in later videos but what's
important to talk about today is let's
say you decided on some ratio whatever
that ratio happens to be how do you
actually go about integrating that into
your diet in order to understand that a
little bit better I think it's important
we cover three topics today number one
we need to talk about the molecular or
chemical structure of these components
from there we can then talk about their
actual function once we understand their
structure and then we'll wrap up today's
video by giving you some actual
application to show you how you can
implement some of those things so you
have the ability to maybe decide on your
own proportions experiment with that a
little bit change them up and see how
you feel so you can be your own
nutritionist to understand what's going
on here we need to understand the
relationship that each macronutrient has
to our body in other words what role is
it actually providing when we consume it
well to start off carbohydrates and fat
are fairly interchangeable because their
basic function is to provide us with
cellular and metabolic energy protein on
the other hand while it can provide
energy is really meant to be structure
so a quick way to think about this is
the silly little analogy I'll have here
let's assume we're out camping and we
need to make a fire if I take newspaper
and if I take wood I'm gonna make an
easy fire these are going to be the fuel
for fire okay now if we look at the
chemical structure which we'll get into
in just a second what we realize is that
carbohydrate ER the newspaper in this
room is a string of carbons fat is also
a string of carbons but a longer stream
so anyone that's made a campfire will
know that a newspaper will give you
maybe a few minutes of fire but it's
gonna burn out really quickly where wood
or a log is gonna give you a lot more
energy over the long term but the
drawback is it's gonna be harder to
ignite all right well
turns out the chemical structure of wood
is a longer chain of carbon kind of
right and so what we have here is paper
being made from wood and these both
being fuels for fire so when we consume
carbohydrate or fat we're using that to
produce us energy and that's why we can
see high fat diets or or high
carbohydrate diets low fat diets and
people can function even in sporting
context pretty well with both because
they're fairly interchangeable where
they differ quite considerably is
protein now protein is like metal all
right now I could in theory if I waited
long enough melt this metal plate here
down and I could get a fire out of it
you can burn metal you're just not going
to get very productive very high
production value out of it all right so
protein is generally not meant to be
used for fuel to power energy however
it's meant to be used of structure to
build things on so if I took my
newspaper and my log here and I lit it
on fire and I melted down some metal I
could reform it and shape it into the
function I wanted to make something
usable so let's talk a little bit more
detail about the structure as we head
back into the garage the reason
carbohydrate and fat is so
interchangeable is because of their
molecular structure now to back up just
a second everything in this universe is
made because we've got several if not
trillions of atoms combined together
connected through things called bonds so
really all a chemical is or a molecule
is or what separates it one from another
is what atoms are in it and what kind of
bonds it has now if we look at
carbohydrate what we realize is
carbohydrate in its most simplest form
alright so when it's floating around
your body in the form of glucose it is a
one two three four five six carbon bond
and if you're not familiar with carbon
that's what makes life alright that's
what the field of organic chemistry is
is the study of carbon if you have
carbon your are considered to be alive
right and so glucose being or sugar in
that match and for the record sugar
carbohydrate glucose it's essentially
the same word right little little
extra bonus knowledge here carbohydrate
and sugars roughly the same word now not
all sugar or excuse me all sugar is a
carbohydrate but not all carbohydrates
are sugar for example fiber fiber as a
card is a carbohydrate that's not a
sugar anyways our most basic form the
fundamental form of energy is this six
carbon chain right so with all of our
bonds in between so if you've seen the
25 minute or the 55 minute physiology of
fat loss videos we talked about how we
derive energy from the breaking and
those molecular bonds well if we look
now when we step back and we look at the
storage form of fat alright so in our
body we tend to to store fat in our
adipose tissue or our subcutaneous fat
and we call that a triglyceride okay now
what that actually is
I missed a couple of bonds there don't
tell a triglyceride is also a
extensively long chains of carbon and
why it's called a triglyceride is tri
meaning three is because it is a 1 2 3
carbon backbone we call that glycerol by
the way and at the at the end of each
glycerol backbone is a free fatty acid
alright so this is a free fatty acid
free fatty acid we'll talk much more
about these in separate videos all right
in fact this is what makes unsaturated
or polyunsaturated fats is whether or
not this is a double bond or or a single
bond right things like that now the
length of the carbon chain of each fatty
acid depends or that's actually what
determines its type so different types
of oils are different types of fats have
different amounts of carbon but this
entire molecule again would be one
triglyceride and so what we can see is
when we compared that to a carbohydrate
we see some significant differences in a
significant single similarities well a
significant difference is the fact that
look how many more total carbons exist
and one molecule of fat and if you
remember we get energy from the breaking
of one bond so what we see here is we
have an excessive or exponentially more
amounts of bonds that we can break with
the one molecule of fat than we can one
molecule of car
hydrate so we're gonna get exceptionally
more energy from breaking down this
entire molecule
I'll get roughly the same amount of
energy per pond broken but we've just
got so many more bonds we can break all
right now the similarity is the fact
that they're molecularly almost
identical and so it's very easy for our
body to kind of go back and forth here
all right I can easily break down a fat
and generate a glucose molecule if I
needed by the inverse I can add a bunch
of these together and form a bunch of
fat if I have to and so again this is
why when we mentioned earlier it is
possible for people to go on low
carbohydrate diets if they have
extremely high fat diets and have enough
energy right because their conversion
back in the respect in fact this is the
point this is the the physiological
point of these molecules is this is
supposed to be your acute form of energy
and this is your backup storage all
right so if we use a silly analogy this
is your gas tank in your car and these
are this is all of the tubs of gasoline
you have out back just in case right
this is your backup generator what we're
trying to do with with our diet in our
normal human evolution is to make sure
that we have an equal balance here
because we want to have some excess fat
around the power stored to power and I
think this backup power but if we
consume too much of either one of these
macronutrients and we have too much
backup we don't like that right obesity
has got an enormous health risk plus the
aesthetic component but this is what
it's for so we have to stop thinking
about fat and carbohydrate as opposing
issues and think about them
synergistically they're meant to work
together it's not bad to have fat it's
not bad to have a carbohydrate this is
also why people tend to say things like
if you eat too many carbs
they'll be stored as fat which is true
the same thing happens when you eat too
much fat right eating too much makes you
fat not eating too much fat so we have
this molecular exchange ability between
fat and carbohydrates we'll talk more
detail that stuff later but we have to
understand the base
poets all right of our carbs looking
like that are fat looking like this
protein though as we mentioned with our
weight plate analogy is very very very
different when you break down protein
you're not gonna have excess amounts of
carbon available what you're gonna have
is a bunch of amino acids and you've all
heard this right amino acids are the
building blocks of proteins this is
really what we're talking about soon
your body when you break down protein
you're gonna break it down into a bunch
of different amino acids inverse if you
want to build a protein you have to
combine together a bunch of amino acids
to make a protein we can go through a
process where we can break these things
down get a couple of carbons and convert
those into a little fat or into a little
carbohydrate for some energy but as we
mentioned outside we don't want to we
want to keep these as structure but we
want to be able to have a full exchange
back and forth here this is an important
concept similar to what some folks will
call metabolic flexibility in other
words you have a physiological capacity
to swing back and forth between burning
fat and carbohydrate as a fuel source
based on your very specific needs so
that you can optimize performance energy
and aesthetics so if we try to put this
into practice this is what it would look
like now I want to cover a couple of
common mistakes to build on we talked
about with the structure and function so
go ahead and come in and take a look at
this first plate now let's assume we're
back to the original pie chart out in
the garage where we talked about maybe
you have an equal third one third one
third split between fat or carbon fat
and carbohydrate all right so vegetables
fruit all carbohydrate I know there's
some fat in here particularly in this
delicious skin but let's just assume
this is all protein this is fat this is
all carbohydrate okay now what most
people are gonna make the mistake of
thinking is I want again we'll just go
with one-third one-third one-third to
make this concept easy to understand and
so they'll think I want one-third
one-third one-third so I will fill my
plate with one-third one-third one-third
easy enough right
the major mistake with that is we have
to realize per gram of protein we get
about four calories per gram of
carbohydrate we also get about four
calories but per gram of fat we get nine
calories so when it comes to being
actually on your plate a split like this
would not be one-third one-third
one-third because even though it is per
size you get over double the amount of
calories from here so we're actually
looking like per calorie is more close
to a fifty percent fat 25% protein 25%
carbohydrate so it's critical that we
understand this if we go ahead and look
at plate number two we say okay we've
made an adjustment we've reduced in fact
I'll bring it back in we've reduced our
fat intake in terms of the amount on our
plate by about half so what this mean
one-third grams carbohydrate one-third
grams of protein half of that amount of
grams of fat to give me one-third
calories carbohydrate one-third calories
fat 1/4 third calories protein but
mistake number two is understanding
which foods are dense in which
macronutrient so you can't just simply
build your plate like this without a
greater understanding for example we see
a big nice delicious hunk of chicken
like that we can actually pretty quickly
calculate the amount of grams and then
we were able to fly that by four to get
the amount of calories that we're
getting from protein but not all food
sources are equal so a great example of
this is our to of carbohydrate sources
okay what we have to realize is even
though our carbohydrates within category
amount is about the same so we have
about the same amount of size of our
cherries as we have of our vegetables we
don't have nearly the caloric density in
vegetables in this particular vegetable
source that we do this fruit source and
so what we'd actually end up happening
here is some of our food sources and
this is true for fat and and protein too
by the way
some of our food sources are more or
less dense per
volume of size on our plate and so again
even though this looked better than our
first attempt because we fixed the
calorie issue we screwed up the volume
issue vegetables are particularly good
one of the many many many reasons why
we're told to eat them you know until we
can't eat anymore is because they occupy
a big volume but they have very very
little actual caloric density meaning
there's probably what Natasha what do
you think how many calories is literally
in this little bit of salad 510 calories
I don't know how many calories are in
these cherries but it's probably triple
quadruple that that's not the saint
cherries are bad and very clearly fruit
is not bad for you fruit does not make
you fat right everything makes you fat
if you eat too much of it but it is a
lot more calorically dense but it's good
for you too right there are a lot of
micronutrients phytochemicals and other
things that are super important in fruit
as well all right so to make our picture
a little bit better
assuming we want to do that one-third
fat one-third carbohydrate one-third
protein a more accurate of plate is
maybe something more like this okay
unless assume that's the same amount of
chicken as before I know this was a
little bit smaller but say we get you
know 25 30 grams of protein right here
so let's go 25 to make the math easy if
I multiply 25 by 4 because of you know
grams for a kcal that means I'm getting
about 100 grant 100 calories of my meal
coming from protein so if I wanted to go
1/3 1/3 1/3 that means this entire plate
needs to be about 300 calories ok since
the calories per gram is double in fact
that means I have to have half the grams
and so if this was 25 grams we'll call
this maybe something like 12 or 10 grams
when I multiply 10 grams by 9 calories
per gram I get 90 calories and so I've
got about 100 calories from protein
about 90 calories from fat and if I want
to get a hundred more calories of
carbohydrate to give me my third my
third my third split my volume on my
plate of this of carbohydrate source
particular
the volume needs to be excessive in
order for me to get 100 actual calories
or 25 grams of carbohydrate okay so this
is confusing and frustrating a lot
because people don't necessarily realize
this particularly the fat issue so
people can tend to overeat fat not that
saying eating a lot of fat is bad for
you it's phenomenal but if we're not
anticipating it being that much we can
overshoot our rough caloric intake by
hundreds or thousands of calories per
day which can be a problem if we're
really focused on trying to make a
weight or we're trying to restrict
calories or increase them for some
reason so by the inverse of that or the
opposite of that fat is that one way to
help yourself add calories if you're in
that boat where you're trying to add
excessive caloric intake you can add a
bunch of nuts or some avocado or some
some wonderful olive oil or something
like this and we could pour this onto
our food add a lot of calories and
almost no volume so hopefully that
helped you understand a little bit about
what the fats protein and carbohydrates
are actually doing in your body you guys
guess you can start calling me the Alton
Brown of physiology right Natasha just
rolled her eyes really heavy right there
so check it out some more of the videos
if you like share them pass them along
to all your friends so we can help get
all this information out to people who
want it and are gonna use it you can
support me at the website Indy galloping
comm any questions or feedback get me on
social I'll be there thanks a lot
you